# **Mohamed Matthew Blango**

SSQ Y1B, Njala University, Njala, Sierra Leone +232 79 313716; +232 31 117523; mmblango@njala.edu.sl; <u>blangomohamed@gmail.com</u>

## PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

Holds a PhD in Agricultural Engineering and has served as Head, Department of Agricultural Engineering (2018-2022) and currently as Acting Dean, School of Technology, Njala University. Since 2011, Dr. Blango has been working on extending cropping into the dry season using a micro-dam rainwater harvesting system. He has taught several courses at the University including Irrigation & Drainage, Land Development, Hydrology and Land Surveying. He has also served as consultant for several Projects supported by the International Fund for Agricultural Development (IFAD) and implemented by the Ministry of Agriculture and Forestry (MAFSL). He has served as Irrigation engineer for a national project implemented by the National Commission for Social Action (NaCSA). Dr. Blango has published several articles in renowned journals in areas including Supplementary Irrigation, Rainwater Harvesting and Agricultural Water management. He has also worked as Principal Investigator for an IAEA sponsored project assessing the effect of a micro-dam rainwater system on artificial recharge of groundwater. In 2015, Dr. Blango was awarded a Borlaug LEAP grant as a PhD scholar, through which he was mentored at the International Rice Research Institute (IRRI) and the University of Illinois, USA for a period of six months. Dr. Blango has also published and reviewed a number of academic papers.

## EDUCATIONAL BACKGROUND/ACADEMIC QUALIFICATION

LEVEL	INSTITUTION	YEAR	DEGREE/DIPLOMA/CERT.
Tertiary	NJALA UNIVERSITY	2017	Ph.D. Agric. Engineering
	NJALA UNIVERSITY	2007	M.Sc Soil and Water Engineering
	NJALA UNIVERSITY COL	. 2003	B. Sc (Hons) Agric .Eng.
Secondar	y BO GOVT. SEC. SCH.	1997	G.C.E 'O' LEVEL (DIV. II)

# WORK EXPERIENCE

DATE OF EMPLOYMENT	DESCRIPTION OF POSITION	ORGANIZATION
Dec. 2005- Mar.2007	Temporary Teaching Assistant (TTA)	National Agricultural Training Centre (NATC), Njala University.
Apr. 2007- Aug. 2018	Lecturer II	Department of Agric. Eng.  Njala University.
Sept. 2018- Sept. 2022	Head of Dept.	Department of Agric. Eng.  Njala University
Oct. 2022 – Present day	Acting Dean, School of Technology	Njala University

# **CONSULTANCIES**

ASSIGNMENT	POSITION	CLIENT	DATE
Mid-Term Review of	CONSULTANT:	National Programme	December, 2014
<b>IACCAPFSL: Small</b>	Inland Valley	Coordination Unit	
Dams in the Inland	Swamp	(MAFFS-SL)/	
Valley Swamp	Specialist International Fund For		
		Agricultural	
		Development (IFAD)	
Rehabilitation and	CONSULTANT:	National Programme	10 – 21 October
Community-based Poverty Reduction	Inland Valley	Coordination Unit	2016.
Project (RCPRP).	Swamp	(MAFFS-SL)/	
<b>Supervision Mission</b>	Specialist	International Fund For	
		Agricultural	
		Development (IFAD)	

Commercialization	nuary- 2
Inland Valley ('ommercialization Rehm	
IIVSIUIIIIIV UIVVUI	uary, 2017.
Agriculture and Food Swamp Programme- Global	
Security Programme (SCP-GAFSP) Specialist Agriculture and Food	
Supervision Mission Security Programme	
(SCP-GAFSP) / Ministry	
of Agriculture Forestry	
and Food Security	
(MAFFS-SL)	
	March,
<b>Community-based Poverty Reduction</b> Inland Valley Coordination Unit (MAFFS-SL)/	
Project (RCPRP) Swamp International Fund for	
Project completion Specialist Agricultural	
mission Development (IFAD)	
<b>Economic Recovery of</b> CONSULTANT: Project Implementation Feb.	2018
<b>Liberian Rice Farmers</b> SRI Specialist Unit (PIU), Ministry of	
in Ebola Affected Agriculture, Government	
Counties of Liberia.	
	oing Since
<b>potential Inland Valley Swamps and Boli Land</b> Engineer Social Policy Analysis Nov.	2018
for irrigation (CESPA)/ National	
infrastructural Commission for Social	
Development in the NaCSA project area  Action (NaCSA)	
TNACADA DEGLECI ATEA ACHOU UNACADA L	
using available data at	
1 0	

# **GRANTS RECEIVED**

ROLE/ POSITION	Supporting Agency	Total Amount (\$)	Date	Title of Project
Principal Investigator/ Project Counterpart (CP)	International Atomic Energy Agency (IAEA)	93,700	January,2014- December, 2016	Assessing the Impact of Rainwater Harvesting technologies on Recharge and Dynamics of Groundwater in an Inland Valley Swamp at Njala
PhD Scholar	Borlaug LEAP Fellowship Programme	20,000	April, 2015- March, 2016	The Performance of a Micro-Dam Rainwater Harvesting System in an Inland Valley Swamp

## TRAINING WORKSHOPS ATTENDED

PRESENTATION	FACILITATOR(S)	DATE	ORGANIZER/LOCATION
TITLE			
Water resource	Professor P. K	January,	Njala University/University
management for	Kalita,	2012	of Illinois
sustainable	University of		
agriculture	Illinois		
	USA		

Surveying and	Professor Richard	January,2013	Njala University/University
GIS for irrigation	Cooke,		of Illinois
and drainage	University of		
	Illinois		
	USA		
Research4life	Professor Dele	September 3-	Research4life and
and TEEAL	Fawole (ITOCA)	6, 2013.	Information Training and
programmes	and		Outreach Centre for Africa
	Dr. Justin Chisenga		(ITOCA)/ Njala University
	(FAO)		
Rice: Research to	Prof. Jan Leach	August 10-	National Science
Production	(Colorado State	28, 2015	Foundation/International
	University)		Rice Research Institute, the
			Philippines.
Water for Food	Dr. Robert Lenton	April 24-26,	Water for Food Daugherty
Global		2016.	Global Institute at the
Conference			University of Nebraska, USA

## **PUBLICATIONS**

## I. Article/Book Chapters in learned journals

- a) **Blango**, **M. M.**, Cooke, R. A., Moiwo, J. P., & Kangoma, E. (2022) Modeling the Effect of Climate Change on Water Stored above a Micro-Dam in an Inland Valley Swamp in Sierra Leone, Using SWAT.
- b) Moiwo, J. P., **Blango, M. M.,** Kawa, Y. K., & Conteh, A. M. (2022). Potential for Sustainable Irrigation towards Food Self-Sufficiency in Sierra Leone. *Emerging Challenges in Agriculture and Food Science Vol. 3*, 99-106.
- c) **Blango**, **M. M.**, Cooke, R. A. C., & Moiwo, J. P., Sawyerr, P.A., Kangoma, E. (2020) Rainwater harvesting for supplemental irrigation under tropical inland valley swamp conditions. Irrigation and Drainage 69 (5), 1095-1105

- d) **Blango**, **M. M.**, Cooke, R. A. C., & Moiwo, J. P. (2019). Effect of soil and water management practices on crop productivity in tropical inland valley swamps. *Agricultural Water Management*, 222, 82-91. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.agwat.2019.05.036">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.agwat.2019.05.036</a>
- e) Moiwo, J.P., Wahab, A., Kangoma, E., **Blango, M.M.**, Ngegba, M.P., Suluku, R. (2019) Effect of Biochar Application Depth on Crop Productivity Under Tropical Rainfed Conditions. *Appl. Sci.* **2019**, *9*, 2602.
- f) Kangoma, E., **Blango**, **M.** M., Rashid-Noah, A.B. Sherman-Kamara J.S., Moiwo, J.P, and Kamara, A (2017). Potential of Biochar-Amended Soil to Enhance Crop Productivity under Deficit Irrigation. Irrig. and Drain. (2017).

### **REFEREES**

#### 1. Dr. A. B Rashid-Noah

Department of Agricultural Engineering Njala University Sierra Leone

Mobile phone: +232 77 800525 Email: rashidnoah@yahoo.com

### 2. Professor Richard Cooke

Department of Agricultural and Biological Engineering

University of Illinois

**USA** 

Mobile phone: +1 217 778 6422

Email: rcooke@illinois.edu